Guide to the George Bernard Shaw Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Bernard Shaw collection
1894-1947
GEN MSS 279
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
The collection consists primarily of letters from Shaw to various correspondents, including Ford Madox Ford, Archibald Henderson, and the firm of T. Fisher Unwin; and writings by Shaw, including an annotated typescript of Arms and the Man and a draft of the Prologue to Caesar and Cleopatra.
Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950
T. Fisher Unwin (Firm)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to George Bernard Shaw, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artifical collection.
English literature -- 19th century; Ford, Ford Madox, 1873-1939; Henderson, Archibald, 1877-1963; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950
- Letters by George Bernard Shaw, 1934 May 12; Series I
  - TLS to A. J. Buttitta. London, 1934 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    With envelope; [addessed in the hand of Blanche Patch, Shaw's secretary]; Accompanied by a TLS from A. J. Buttitta to Archibald Henderson, dated 1933 Feb 11; Gift, 1937.
  - Autograph Postcard signed to Norman Clark. London, 1929 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gift, 1937.
  - Typewritten copy of letter to Mr. Cox. London, 1919 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift, 1943.
  - TLS to Mrs. E. L. Edwards. London, 1920 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    With envelope; Purchase, 1959.
  - TLS to Earl E. Fisk. London, 1919 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Removed from his Heartbreak House, 1919. Purchase, 1963.
  - ALS to Ford Madox Ford. London, 1909 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Purchase, 1967.
  - ALS to W. Courthope Forman, Jr. London, 1900 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Concerns the career of Alma Murray; Removed from his Plays, Pleasant, and UnpleasAnt, 1898; Gift.
  - TLS with autograph postscript, to The Forum Publishing Co. London, 1924 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Accompanied by envelope addressed to Archibald Henderson in the hand of Blanche Patch, Secretary to Shaw; Also Carbon copy, with signature and postscript in the hand of Blanche Patch; Gift, 1937, 1960.
  - 9 letters and 7 autograph postcards to Archibald Henderson, 1904-31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift, 1936, 1937.
  - 4 TLS and 2 APS to Archibald Henderson, 1906-08 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift, 1959.
  - 2 ALS to [Archibald Henderson]. London, 1924-32 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    The note of 1932 Sep 9 is accompanied by a typewritten receipt for payment for a license to reproduce a photograph of Shaw, signed L. J. Lewis, Malven, 1932 Sep 5; Gift, 1937.
  - 2 complimentary cards of George Bernard Shaw, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    With an envelope addressed to Archibald Henderson, in the hand of Blanche Patch, G. B. Shaw's secretary; Gift, 1937.
  - Autograph postcard signed to John Lane. London, 1894 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Found in his "The Case for Equality", London, 1913; Gift, 1937.
  - ALS to Mary Ethel McAuley. London, 1920 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Gift, 1973.
  - Letter to Julie Moore (carbon copy). London, 1909 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - TLS to Robert Nichols. London, 1922 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Gift, 1954.
  - ALS to Edward Pease. Maybury Knoll, Woking, 1903 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Purchase, 1963.
  - TLS to William Kean Seymour. London, 1917 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Purchase, 1975.
  - 20 Letters to T. Fisher Unwin, (typed copies), 1888-1916 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Printed card addressed to autograph collectors. London (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Accompanied by envelope with manuscript note in an unidentified hand; Gift, 1937.
- Writings of George Bernard Shaw, 1894; Series II
  - Arms and the Man, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
    Typescript, signed; bound in three notebooks; Inscribed by Shaw: "No.3. Mr. Lewis Weighton."; Apparently an acting copy for Mr. Weighton, with manuscript directions and cues dictated by Shaw; Gift, 1956.
  - Caesar and Cleopatra: "Prologue" (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Typescript, signed; Accompanied by 2 TLS concerning the prologue from Blanche to Alwin Scheuer, 1929 Apr 4, and J. C. C. Taylor, 1930 Nov 11; Gift.
  - Caesar and Cleopatra, 1904 Dec? (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Printed program of the copyright performance, at Newcastle-on-Tyne, 1899 Mar 15; with annotations in Shaw's hand; Accompanied by envelope addressed in Shaw's hand to Archibald Henderson, 1905 Jan 17; Gift, 1937.
  - Mrs. Warren's Profession, 1920 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Typescript of an article for the Pittsburgh Dispatch, with corrections and additions in Shaw's hand; Gift, 1973.
  - "Report on Manifesto", 1898 Aug (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Sixty Years of Fabianism", 1947 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Galley proof with AMs corrections, signed and dated; Purchase, 1963.
- Other Papers, 1908-11; Series III
  - Shaw, Charlotte Frances Payne-Townshend, "Mrs. Bernard Shaw". ALS and autograph postcard signed to Archibald Henderson. London, 1908-11 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Printed Contract (blanks filled in by Shaw), for Performance of You Never Can Tell by the Compton Repertory Company. London, 1918 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Virginia Compton listed as manager; Purchase, 1956.
  - 8 photographs and illustrations (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Submitted by Archibald Henderson to Shaw as candidates for reproduction in his biography of Shaw; with manuscript annotations by Shaw; Also photographs of Shaw; Gift, 1937, 1962.